[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
let's begin uh welcome to the stoa
everyone
i'm peter limberg the steward of the
stoa still is a place for us to cohere
and
dialogue about what matters most at the
knife's edge of this very moment
and today we have anthony magna bosco
street epistemologist extraordinaire
for those of you who do not know what
street epistemology is uh
we'll get into that like a brief
one-on-one anthony was on
my former podcast which was rebranded to
the stoa
we had a good one-on-one so i'll share
that into the um the chat and the show
notes and stuff like that
but yeah so how today's gonna go um
we're gonna jam
me and anthony about uh street
epistemology and then how it relates to
culture war
and if you have any questions throw them
in the chat
and i'll call you and meet you when we
get to the the collective questioning
portion if you want me to read on your
behalf just let me know indicate that in
the chats
and i will read it on your behalf
because this will go on youtube
um most people are familiar faces here
but there is some uh newcomers which is
uh you know welcome
to the store that being said i will
allow anthony to unmute himself and take
him in
how's it going my friend you're a mute
right now
there we go there we go hey what's going
on peter thanks for having me on your
show
i see some familiar some familiar faces
here this is great
and a lot of unfamiliar ones which is
even better honestly thanks for having
me on your show
yeah my pleasure man uh i've been
meaning to get um
you and essie uh on uh i've been a fan
and following
as you know since i wrote that white
paper um
on the culture yeah maybe get like a
show of hands for those who have their
camera on
who's familiar with se or straight up
estology like the method
at all so just on the one panel that i
saw i saw
half the hands go up but there may be
some bias there they may have been the
first to join who knows
interesting so maybe like okay
i'll yeah i'll but i'll just hand over
to you um
what is street epistemology street
epistemology
is a technique that was started by a
philosophy press professor in portland
who was familiar with the socratic
method
and i think used it personally with his
interactions and he started realizing
hey
if you use questions to explore claims
you can probably help another person
help that person take another look at
their views
so um he wrote a book called a manual
for creating atheists which
he uh he gave a talk at the freedom from
religion foundation in 2012. i was just
looking at this video
i saw i was in that crowd watching him
speak where he was talking a little bit
about his book
i think i bought his book then but i may
have gotten it later i don't
exactly remember but it's um
it's where you use questions to explore
claims with people on sensitive topics
so
rather than arguing with people or
giving them facts
or or talking over them or or allowing
them to misrepresent your position
you basically just let the person that
you're talking to explain their position
and you ask them questions to drive down
to the reliability of their method
that's it that's kind of it in a
nutshell it's it's expanded a lot since
he wrote his first book
in fact he wrote a second book called
how to have impossible conversations
which i think given the two choices i
think i'd advise people to check that
book out first
because i think he's taken a lot of the
things that we've learned and he's
learned
since the first book and bake that into
his
his second book so yeah it's where you
you basically explore claims that people
make
in a respectful way where you're asking
questions and it's
it's it's uh it's kind of interesting to
watch that happen
most people i think can grasp
street epistemology better if they watch
examples of people doing it rather than
just me talking about it
so if you haven't already watched some
examples i'd recommend that you do that
have you seen a lot of them peter i've
seen a bunch yeah
yeah there's nothing like watching
people ponder the deeply held belief
that they've held for the longest time
and start to wonder why the hell do i
think that this is true
and that's usually what happens during
these talks
and so uh kind of like the the histo
historical lineage of it
and we were chatting about this when we
spoke last time uh
i i playfully labeled the street
epistemologist as like
friendly new atheists um because they're
the new atheists have this vibe they're
very combative with challenging people
in religious
debate stage and then uh sc or people
who are trained in it
you know the social fluency that hey
excuse me we have you know
i got a few questions inquiries and it's
very kind of implying uh the principle
of charity
all these different kind of
conversational techniques to make the
person comfortable
but then really getting at the core of
why they believe what they believe
um do you think that's unfair of me to
call it like a friendly new atheist like
how did you how would you see that kind
of
no no in fact i was really excited when
i saw that you characterized
street epistemologists as sort of an
offshoot of the new atheists because i
think
i think your characterization of the new
atheist movement is fairly correct it
was
it was it was aggressive it was in your
face
and it it held nothing back um
and it got a lot of people's attention i
was more comfortable coming out as an
atheist and getting involved in the
atheist
movement or community because i was
watching examples of dawkins and harris
and denet
dillahunty etc that was really exciting
to me as somebody who was watching
people walk around with beliefs that i'm
i don't think are true
so it got my attention but
what i think happens is that people then
try to mimic those aggressive approaches
with the people in their lives that they
love
and that can really backfire so the the
street epistemology approach
um i think is an offshoot of the new we
sometimes we joke around say
the street epistemologist is the new new
atheist
sort of a nicer gentler more empathetic
type of atheist but
there are moments where people who are
promoters and practitioners of this
method we still slip into our very
aggressive ways
it's hard to not debate for the rest of
your life
you're still going to probably do that
but if you if you value the relationship
and you want to help the person take
another look at their views
it seems like the se approach is more
effective
and um like when i wrote the memetic
tribes culture war paper i listed
uh sc asymmetric tribe on the
spreadsheet i shared in the chat
and that's how i think uh peter picosian
uh
tagged you into like we got each other's
radar i think that that way
um and i've interviewed you and peter on
my podcast we chatted
and it'd be interesting to kind of
discuss the distinction between uh
essie as like a mimetic tribe as like a
tribal constellation
and sc as an actual method yeah
that's an important distinction and i
got really excited when i saw your i
never thought about
i never thought about a culture war or
memetic tribes until i saw your
spreadsheet and then
the light bulb sort of went off for me
like oh that's a really interesting way
to think about it and i was really
pleased to see somebody
looking at street epistemology and
seeing it as potentially its own
sort of tribe or community or movement
because since peter wrote that book in
2012 or 2013 thousands of people are
getting into this approach
it's gaining momentum there definitely
is a community
there's thousands of people in a discord
server or several discord servers
there's thousands of people on
on reddit or facebook or twitter that
are getting involved in it
but just because you might be in the sc
community doesn't mean that um
well you don't have to be in the se
community to use the
i'm abbreviating street epistemology to
sc sorry i tend to do that
but um you can be in any tribe
and adopt the tools that are being
developed by the street epistemology
community
that's the neat thing about what i think
we're doing in street epistemology
is that there's this community that's
that's honing these tools
for more effective and productive talks
these tools can be used by anyone in any
memetic tribe
in fact we want people to use these
tools if you learn these tools
i'm hoping that you take them back to
your tribe
and you teach them how to use them as
well so i think the street epistemology
tribe
for a lack of a better
nomenclature i think um
i think that works out really good like
i think that's a really good useful way
of viewing it because
um we're out there we're hammering away
at this we're trying to put these tools
together and we're encouraging people to
use them
and i have some really strong feelings
about this tool i think this tool
honestly matt i think that this tool is
going to be
this tool will be around through the
culture war to the end of it
it will be it's not going away it's
definitely not going away
so i think the sooner that people in
these various tribes learn about this
method
of communicating with each other the
better
you will have a leg up your tri will
have a leg up if you adopt these tools
and use them that's my personal view on
it
and um so to echo that at first i uh if
you
are not familiar with the method it's a
really tight
method it's a really good method um and
i do agree it could be repurposed
uh by different sort of tribes and i
even suggested that
in the past writing uh where like like
an agnostic i'm more sort of an agnostic
uh
an agnostic kind of like tribal
constellation if you will
and you can use that you know for for
the the sc method for that as well
but like here's like a tough question
you asked me feel free to give it a
tough question
please is the hardest the better is this
sort of like a like a sneaky trojan
horse on your part like like
okay like you know take the method and
then you use it then you're sort of like
you know
if you use it earnestly and honestly and
authentically you'll undermine your own
epistemology and foundation great great
question i'm really glad you asked it um
regardless of how i answer this i think
uh yes it's it's it's a it is a trojan
horse i think
i think there's a trojan horse aspect of
it of of it
because once you start using this method
on other people's claims you will use it
on your own claims
and you will yeah you'll start to use it
on yourself so in that aspect that was
one of the most revealing things about
this approach was
when you start using it frequently you
turn it on your own views and you become
a lot more
careful about what you claim to know is
factually the case
and that's an important distinction many
times we're just giving our opinions
we're we're stating opinions as fact but
here's my perspective when people start
learning street epistemology
you tend to be a little bit more
cautious about what you claim to know is
the truth and you tend to be a little
bit more accepting
of the claims that people are making
because they probably just haven't
thought it through
or had anyone kick the tires on on the
belief that they're
that they're holding so it's been a it's
been a net positive
so it's a it's a weird trojan horse in
that
um you almost you almost sort of hop on
the horse yourself
you know what i'm saying like you start
to realize the benefits to the approach
and then you become a champion of it
within your own tribe and i think that's
what's going to happen
people are going to start to see other
people talking about racism
um veganism religion
trump you name it but we're having
respectful productive
productive talks and that's not
happening today
i mean look at almost everything you see
on the news almost everything that you
see on youtube
is argument and strawmenting
misrepresenting
tearing people down trying to make
people look stupid that's not exact
that's not at all what we're doing with
se
this is try to this is to get clarity in
your position
so that it's clear to yourself not just
to me who's asking you these questions
but to bring clarity to your own views
and that's something that's extremely
valuable now there are some um
there are some holes in the armor i
suppose of the approach there's some
certain
aspects of it that i think are um
might slow us down a little bit like
it's confusing it could be a little
boring it might be a little tough to
learn
uh it's hard to set aside your ego and
set aside your own view when somebody
says something that's like
like i just uploaded a video where
somebody said you can't be moral without
believing that there's a god well
three years ago i would have lost my
[ __ ] if i had heard that
but now i just i just roll with it and i
ask questions and we end up
making progress on it so um there's
certain hurdles that i think people have
to overcome in order to be
to grasp the method and to use the
method
but once you once you once you much
once you mature enough once you mature
enough
to understand what's going on with this
tool
it changes you and it changes your
interactions for the better
that's that's been my experience over
the eight years or so that i've been
doing this
did it um sort of weaken or strengthen
the belief system that you had going
before
you learned the method and started
applying it
which which beliefs like atheism or
something either yeah either
atheism as a whole or maybe this uh
certain beliefs that you you
might have held there have been some
beliefs that have changed my view on
views on because i've engaged with
people on these topics about gun control
and abortion
and god and all this other stuff so when
you have hundreds and hundreds of
conversations where you're using this
approach
it does it does tend to change your own
perspective on some things
um one thing that i've noticed that it
tends to happen to most people who learn
this
is they they tend to back off of their
dogmatism
on their own views and that's extremely
useful
because now i could be more open to
considering somebody else's
perspective that maybe hinduism is true
or or that maybe trump really is the
best president for our country at this
period of time
um having an open mind is one of those
hurdles i think that you have to sort of
you have to be willing to adopt that
when you use this approach
you have to be willing to say okay i
actually might be mistaken
on these core beliefs that i hold i
should really be open to hearing what
they have to say now
this isn't agreeing to disagree this is
pushing back
but pushing back in a way where it's
respectful
and again productive uh
so the other question i had was um
about uh the cult so the theme title of
this whole talk was culture work 2.0
yeah and uh there's two memes like uh
i wrote that white paper called the mega
tribes culture 2.0 then peter piccolian
wrote something called he stole
the title and he called cultural 2.0 and
he had a different meaning which i want
to talk about in a moment about like the
great realignment and grievance studies
and stuff
yeah yeah uh how i viewed it is like
this
multi-polar war like that spreadsheet
where there's like multiple different
tribes
and reality tunnels that are coexisting
and
like right now for example you have uh
black lives matter you have antifa
you have q anon you have extinction
rebellion you have all these militias
and they don't are not all buddies with
each other they have odd alliances at
times
but they have different world views um
and then you hinted earlier that the
this technique this this method is going
to play a critical
role in the culture and then so taking
this frame of all these different
reality tunnels coming at you
how do you how do you think this could
be the case
all right that's a good question and
i've never really verbalized this so
listeners please be a little bit
charitable because i'm still trying to
form
my my vision of how this is playing out
but it seems like
it seems like um this is how i'm
envisioning it like after i read your
spreadsheet then i've been going out and
having talks with people on a wide
variety of claims
and uploading some of those to my
youtube channel
it seems like some tribes there's an
important distinction when we look at
how many tribes are in your spreadsheet
now i i haven't checked it recently
well i haven't updated it but there was
like 30-something okay
this is what i would love to see with
your spreadsheet i think it's it kind of
ties everything together i would love to
see you at a column
that says something like views truth in
objective terms
yes no the tribes that view truth and
are going to be the ones that make it
through the culture war
if you if you think narrative can be
accepted as truth or you think opinion
is the same thing as fact
if you think subjective truth is on
equal footing as objective truth
you're not you're probably not going to
make it through the culture war i don't
think that that's the case i think
that's a prerequisite
and i think it would be a really fun
exercise and i don't know how you do it
because
you can talk to 50 people from a tribe
and you might get mixed results but
that's okay
because the people who view truth and
objective terms within those tribes
can learn these tools and bring them to
the people that don't
that i think is going to be the biggest
delimiter delimiter
in those different tribes so that's one
way of looking at it um
this is a tool that can be used by
anyone in these tribes
now you mentioned like alliances
there's some interesting things going on
in this culture war
there really are like we're seeing
atheists working with theists
what do they have in common well they
think that truth is
objective now in my view
many theists i don't i don't i think
theists think they have the objective
truth but i don't think that they do
and i've had thousands of conversations
with theists who think that they do
and it almost comes down to faith and
that is a that is an unreliable
epistemology we can quibble about
definitions and everything and i'm sure
there's a lot of theists that disagree
with that
that no faith is the thing that you get
after you decide that god is real or
whatever
but for the most part what i think is
we're going to start if you watch for
this peter i think that this is going to
happen
i think you'll notice that the tribes
that view truth or
or agree that truth is objective they're
going to start coalescing they're going
to start working together
to gosh i i hate this metaphor of a
battle
but um at the moment it seems like it's
the best way of looking at it
like i think that these tribes are going
to be clashing with each other
and it's largely because of the way that
we view
the nature of reality and whether we
think truth is objective or not
so we're going to start noticing very
odd alliances
those alliances won't last forever
especially when your ally starts
slipping into relativism and it's okay
that i believe that's true because i
take it on faith in this type of stuff
but for the moment
this is what i think you're going to
start noticing
and this is what's sort of uh it's like
an extent what you said was an extended
version of what peter picosian called
culture 2.0
uh or the great alignment uh and if let
me see if i can get it and let me know
if i got it
please because i i you know maybe i
internalize what he said and i'm just
repackaging or something but that's been
it's been months since i've read his
article so yeah if you want to go ahead
and paraphrase it or something i'd
be glad to listen to it yeah and so my
understanding of that was pretty much
what you said but he focused more on the
kind of christians and then atheists and
how the the atheist movement got split
between sort of like the woke
social justice stream and then more of a
kind of the
liberal side and then the liberal side
they find this odd alliance
with the christians um and then he says
this is the great
realignment and um i think that's
similar what you said but you have a
more expanded scope like this this
constellation of tribes are going to
merge around
right well yes and one that has maybe
like a standpoint epistemology or
something like that
yeah i think i take a more broader
perspective but this is one thing that
i've noticed with um
peter and james and helen and other
people who are
they're focusing too much on one tribe
the idea that the problem of
subjectivity
being accepted as fact is something that
cuts across
hundreds of groups millions of people
so again i've been thinking this through
and and um peter always talks about this
idea of parahisia of like speaking truth
in the face of of uh power or something
so i
and these are friends of mine
if you remember remember back to uh
emmanuel for creating atheists
this was a book that was teaching this
method of street epistemology
for atheists to use with theists it was
very
narrowly focused and atheists like
myself picked up on it
we started going out and intentionally
having conversations with theists
to figure out if they have a reliable
epistemology for god
and one thing that we quickly realized
is that the tool can be used for all
different types of claims
in fact if you if you look at people who
do se
it's it's it's the percentage of people
who talk about religion
is probably less than 40 percent now
maybe even 30.
we're shifting to political topics we're
shifting to vaccines mask usage
vegan eating meat all this stuff so just
like a manual for creating atheists may
have been too narrow or too
too laser focused on one group it's
conceivable that
um the grievance studies and
and this idea you know focusing on woke
um
doing doing uh doing this thing about
like
what was it called um
what was the hoax called grievance
studies hoax that was very targeted to
one
demographic of people why was that
like i understand why they may have
selected that because they're very close
to it
they are they're all i think in academia
so it kind of makes sense that they
focused on that but
what i'm suggesting here is that we
might want to we might want to zoom out
just a little bit
i think we're focused too much on one
group and i think there's a variety of
different groups there are people in the
republican party or the democratic party
for example who view truth in subjective
terms
and we could be missing that by being so
focused on one small
aspect on one small tribe
that concerns me i i think it might be
healthy to
to zoom out a little bit and and see
what's what's the main
factor here and which tribes is it
intersecting
and try to tackle it from a broader
perspective
does that make sense yeah um it reminds
me of kind of what happened to peterson
where you know
he he wasn't really a cultural warrior
at first when like i knew him before um
he even entered the whole kind of
cultural scene but he sort of got
captured in the battle and got like
hardened in it and i see the same thing
with the cozy and
especially james lindsay with his
twitter game
so and so what i'm saying what i'm
getting from you is that
by tethering yourself to the methodology
and not so much
like the the battle field or the battle
like the particular battle like in more
of the methodology then you can kind of
apply it not just to
one woke tribe you can apply to like a
humanoid tribe or a reactionary tribe or
whatever
right that's kind of the nature of of
street epistemology
uh as it is because once you learn the
technique of asking questions like we do
in street epistemology where we don't
we don't get so focused on the claim we
we're semi interested in the reasons and
making sure that that's the real reason
why you think that your claim is true
but it's the methodology that a person
is using
to verify the quality of their reasons
for thinking something is true
that is something that cuts across every
type of claim that you can make
so once you learn street epistemology
se um you'll you'll start to recognize
the efficiency of it because it almost
does it doesn't even matter the claim
it doesn't matter what claim people are
making what's what's more important is
did you build this belief on a solid
foundation let's probe that foundation
how reliable is it is your confidence in
your claim justified
that's a game changer because now we're
not talking about specific claims or
anything at all like that
and it kind of distances the the person
from
the belief we're no longer talking about
your your view that god is real or that
so-and-so is the best president or that
we need to start teaching uh critical
race theory
in businesses or something you can
actually get down to the reliability of
the method that a person is using
and once people start to realize
that i'm using a method that's
unreliable for this claim
oh shoot there's 30 other claims that i
use that same method for
you start to see how efficient this can
be so
so this is wildly exciting to see
people starting to pick up on these
tools and use them in a variety of
different
fields with a variety of different
mimetic tribes
so i'm going to pivot to the the chat uh
like i haven't been following so
please plus one any questions plus one
yourself so i can kind of like
yeah i'm not following it either just so
now i just heard some thunder so
hopefully we don't lose the power or
anything here
cool cool uh so ask one more question um
paul vander clay came
on last week it was really quick great
session we called it
being a christian in culture war 2.0 and
he said something that was like wow like
it give me pause um
he said that culture wars are great
practice
uh for being a christian um because
the christians uh are the only tribe in
his opinion
that loves their enemies uh so it's like
kind of like practicing that that the
christian love
um and then like i'm like i'm not here
to dispute that claim but the question
is is your
for for someone an se is do you do you
think that's a healthy frame to have
that the culture war is a good practice
and if so what to practice what excuse
me um
well in order to be good at street
epistemology you need you need to
approach it from a place of empathy
which i suppose is similar to love um
you have to i guess you have to like or
love people
if you care enough to engage with them
about the claims that they're making
that might be one of the best
expressions of love is to gently push
back when somebody says something
that's questionable so
i mean listen christians don't have a
lock on love okay
you can be a loving human being and not
believe in any god so let's let's
dispatch with that notion right away
what you need to do to be good at this
and be successful at at
respectfully interrogating claims is to
take your ego
and set it aside so if christians can do
that they're going to be really good at
sc
if muslims can do that they're going to
be really good at se if hindus can do
that or atheists can do that or whatever
you're going to probably be really good
at se so um
i guess there sort of is an element of
love when you do this
like you can use this tool and and use
to harm people i suppose or bash them
or make yourself feel good by watching
somebody struggle to answer questions i
suppose that's the case
but generally i think
most of the people that i've met that
get into this
do this because they want to help other
people
and not from the point of view of like
i've got it all figured out
so let me go help these poor misled
folks
like i want i want you peter to learn
this method to challenge me on the
claims that i make
i want paul to learn these these these
tools so that he can use it the next
time he's talking to a mormon
or a muslim or an atheist
cool all right so um let's pivot to the
the chats
uh christian wants me to read this on
his behalf
uh what does anthony's christian i'm
sorry did you say a christian or
somebody
the name christian christian so um
what is anthony's thoughts on
metaphorical truth uh i think this is
brett weinstein's
uh term i don't know if you're familiar
with it yeah
and i'm asking i wonder if the
pursuit of truth is anthony's highest
value
the pursuit of truth the pursuit
i don't think we could ever know
anything for sure so i don't think we'll
ever
actually be able to touch the truth i
think it would get fairly close to it
but the pursuit of it is one of my
highest
values yeah and
figuring out which views that i'm
holding that i can't justify
to myself and getting rid of those so
that's that's one of my highest
that is one of my highest values is
objective
and yes i've heard of metaphoric truth
and
uh what's the other one i heard dramatic
truth
the most recent video that i uploaded
somebody was mentioning well
it's this do you mean dramatically true
i'm like no i mean like the objective
factual truth of the matter
so i do see a lot of people it's really
interesting
it's really really interesting what i'm
noticing with theists where
i think theists realized that they this
is this is a bold claim and i'm willing
to have somebody challenge
challenge me on this later but theists
it seem
they don't have evidence to back up
their claim
many people base their theistic views on
faith
which when we define it we realize it's
probably an untestable trust
trust and untestable trust and that is
unreliable
and now what i see is lots of theists
getting really excited about this idea
of dramatic truth
or or what did you call it what was the
other one that you did you call it
dramatic
metaphorical metaphoric truth um
i just i have these little box of tic
tacs have you seen
have you seen these running around the
internet lately we've been throwing mean
memes up and stuff sometimes we meet
people who say
it's true to me because i get value from
it
or um it's my
truth that type of stuff uh
i'm a better person because i think that
it's true and that's good enough for me
to think that it's true
so when we meet people who view truth in
subjective terms like that
we usually ask something like do you
think the total number of pieces in this
box is either even or odd and it can't
be both
that one little simple thought
experiment can help people
realize that they are viewing truth in
objective terms for most
everything else in their life but when
it comes to the deeply held beliefs that
are important to them
suddenly there's this valuable there's
this valuable dramatic truth
or metaphoric truth that suddenly
becomes available to them and they glom
onto it because it's so lovely and
beautiful
it makes me feel good and i'm allowed to
now have this belief
because i'm now calling i'm now
redefining truth to allow me to have it
you can do that but for the people who
are sitting at the the
the mimetic tribes that are sitting at
this big round table of
infinite seats um in order to sit at the
table you need to view truth in
objective terms
there's a seat waiting for you we want
you there
okay but there's there's um there's a
hurdle that you have to overcome to sit
there
and that is the recognition that while
metaphoric truth or dramatic truth
might make you feel good it's not
it's not a reliable way for coming to
the actual truth of the matter
cool
[Music]
does there anybody want do you have a
follow-up for that um oh yeah
christian didn't i i read on his behalf
okay um
uh i'll call on you for the next
question
now i should also add though um i do i
do think that there are people
who need to hold on to beliefs that they
can't justify
to themselves or other people because
they think that they may become a bad
person and maybe they really
they really think that they would maybe
they really would become bad
hold on to your dramatic truth okay but
um
but you might want to back off of your
involvement with the big decisions that
need to be made
in our culture leave that to the people
who view truth in objective terms
now again these are ideas that have been
that have been eating at me for
for years now and it wasn't really until
i saw your your spreadsheet and started
thinking about all these different
tribes and how they're viewing these
things
that it's sort of coalescing i could be
way off on this
um i don't think that i am though this i
really think that this is
this is a really useful lens to kind of
look at it through
rain you had a question hey anthony
um i wanted to ask about
um objectivism because you've used that
word a bit
and um i'm curious if you have a
distinction
between objectivism and scientific
materialism
um and i'm curious what you think about
a sort of
pure um empiricist view like uh the only
thing that's real
is what we can measure and observe
there's i i always hold out a little bit
of myself to be open to the idea that
there might be something more than the
physical world
that we can rigorously test as best we
can well
test as best we can using the tools of
the scientific method
but i don't know how we would actually
be able to verify that it's the case
without
some sort of scientific or or um
or you know rigorous testing process to
see if it's the case
so i'm open to hearing and i've talked
to thousands of people who think that
there's a supernatural realm or there's
something more than
than this one world or this one life
that we have
i i haven't become jaded on it let me
just say but
when you when you run into so many
people who
who hold views that they can't test
methodologies that they can't test the
reliability of
um yet they're so confident that they
have the factual truth of the matter
it's quite frustrating to see it time
and time again
so um that's kind of how i view things
yeah i think
um the time to actually hold a high
degree of confidence in the truth of
something
is when it could be demonstrated to be
the case why would we want to do
anything else now
i'm open to there being a god or or
there being some sort of supernatural
realm or maybe karma really is real
or something along those lines but um if
we can't demonstrate to be the case
we probably shouldn't be so confident
that it's factually true
um can i follow up on that peter
um thanks that makes sense um
i'm i'm a realist for what it's worth so
i
i uh i don't tend to to fall on the
supernatural
um side of things so much um but i'm
wondering about
uh again that sort of objectivism as the
independent
um the independent truth of things
that they're true um independently of us
of the observer
and um so like everything you said about
being able to verify
uh those claims uh seems to
i agree that's the only way to get to
truth but the verification process
itself would seem to involve
a subjective observer have you thought
about that problem of
where the subjective observer fits in
with the objective scientific study
yeah you're always going to have that
element of of
individuals observing what's happening
and then their subjective interpretation
of it but it seems like
if there's if there's attributes of of
uh
repeatability of testability to
feasibility
seeing if other people can reproduce
your results
that are from different cultures or
different tribes
yes you'll still always have those those
biases that we bring to it
i don't think that there's a way that we
can ever completely mitigate for our own
biases
we're going to always bring it bring
that to the table unfortunately
but if we're aware of it and we try to
mitigate it
and we recognize that it could be
influencing our perception of the true
reality of the situation
that's what we need to do but that's not
what we're seeing we don't tend to see
that a lot these days
we tend to see a lot of people who say
well that's been my experience
so therefore it's factually it's a fact
that affects everybody because of my own
personal experience
it's a very dangerous way of looking at
the world and interacting with the world
and that's the thing that i think is so
useful about this
this dialectical approach is that uh
it tries to reframe things i think from
an object an objective
observer's point of view um
i should also mention that uh like when
i talk to somebody and use this approach
i'm completely open to them using the
same technique on my own
views and maybe uncovering some biases
that i have
maybe i'm a little bit more maybe i'm a
little bit
more um skeptical when it comes to
theistic claims that i should be
um that that's something i probably
never would have admitted five years ago
or six years ago
but having practiced this method you
start to you start to realize the
frailties of your own
perceptions of things so
yeah i i don't know if i want to add
anything more to that
all right um uh
let's go paul you had a question about
emotional intelligence
yeah so it seems like um
a major piece of this if i'm getting it
right um is
the emotional intelligence required to
sort of
be curious and rather than sort of
defensive about your own beliefs and
sort of
um putting that aside what maybe give
the cliffs notes version and i can go to
the website later but what's the close
notes version of
how essie deals with that because i
think everybody's coming from a
different place in their life and their
own eq
maybe just talk a little bit about that
okay
that's a really good point and if you
look at my earlier videos
my emotional intelligence
was uh was very nascent it was very very
immature i was still developing it i was
still trying to
crush my opponents with facts and data
[Music]
the best way to get good at street
epistemology where you use where you're
using questions to
respectfully challenge people's claims
uh
in a product in a productive way i think
almost requires
a certain level of maturity to be good
at it now there are
there are people who understand the
techniques
like oh i understand like where the
conversation should probably go and
what's a good question
to ask but what tends to happen
is that uh practitioners of this
approach they tend to let their own
emotions get in the way
so it's been a really kind of humbling
experience over the years i was just
counting on my fingers uh before this
call i think it was like i've been doing
this for like seven years
and having hundreds of conversations
with people
one thing that's been really helpful in
in helping me mature as a practitioner
of this method
and developing my own um my own
emotional intelligence is getting
is having a talk uploading it to youtube
and then watching people critique me
and you have you guys watch you guys
look at youtube comments right they're
not usually very nice
so i was getting some very blunt direct
feedback
as far as what i was doing how i was
doing it
she looked really uncomfortable when you
ask those questions why didn't you end
the conversation sooner
there are certain things that you find
yourself develop developing when you
not only practice this approach but you
have other people in the community
giving you feedback and then also
watching yourself later
like recording yourself um just a little
quick tip for somebody
uh who wants to try this pretend that
100 people are watching you
when you're having your next
conversation
you'll probably notice that you're going
to be on your probably a little bit
nicer behavior a little bit more
charitable in your interpretations
and that i think you might actually be
able to sort of
tweak tweak your emotional intelligence
by
by sort of framing it in that way but um
it's definitely something that i think
people might
naturally have some people naturally
have it some people don't but for the
people that don't naturally have it
i'm optimistic that you can you can
overcome your own handicaps
and develop your emotional intelligence
i do think that that's possible
it's not easy and it might become more
natural to some people than others
but i definitely think it's doable and i
definitely think it's
it's probably one of the most important
factors in being good at se
is learning how to to
[Music]
learning how to human be a human see
other people as human beings
if you can do that you're going to be
really good at this
uh any follow-up paul
no i'm good thank you that was great
yeah thanks paul appreciate it
dan feldman you had 20 questions uh do
you want to um
pick one i i don't know if i
had did i have a question can you copy
and paste uh
an actual question i asked um i actually
i think there was one that was an actual
question but i i
i think that was an early one and it may
have already been answered
um i was just gonna say i think we also
may have some volunteers dropping in
links to to certain groups or
like we have a website for this and a
discord server and a reddit and all this
stuff so
if this is even remotely intriguing to
your followers peter like there's
a ton of resources out there for people
who want to learn more about it
yeah um we'll drop a few links uh i
think the links are just being populated
right now
uh dan did you have any kind of
statement or follow-up um
your questions were yeah i mean i guess
i guess i
you know i do
i do coaching i do uh executive uh and
professional coaching and i've
also been involved with empathy circles
and
um i think just socratic question
i was trained as an engineer and also
you know with science and stuff like
that and so
to me socratic questioning just seems
like
the natural way of behaving in the world
and and i think it's also one of the
ways in which
i i i've encountered a lot in my life
just people who
say outlandish things and so it's just
it's my way of like
um engaging with them well i
i turn off my own position like i don't
i don't
i don't care what's true or not let's
let's let's play with this
but usually what happens is
contradictions are revealed
and then you go further in those
questions and depending on how
emotionally intelligent the other person
is they either get angry at you or
walk out of the room or if they're open
and they
they um
are committed to an ideal or a value
such as
integrity and soundness and honor and
things like that
then they will actually try to discover
what the truth is with you but i
i don't know yeah yeah
i could what do you find with regard to
that and your encounters i guess
with the world and your approach
my my experience tells me that
people do want to believe true things
and that when it comes down to it
um okay there people
in my experience people do want to
believe true things and they often think
that they have the truth
but then there's another layer i guess
of people who say
i'm starting to understand that i don't
have good reasons for thinking that it's
true
but it's more important for me to hold
this belief and think that it is
like the value that i get from it
supersedes the need for me to be holding
on to
objectively true beliefs so in that
respect like there's there's different
people
i've i've met people who say i think
karma is real and five minutes later
just after them defining what it meant
they said
i don't believe that anymore like that
that's an interesting quality to see in
people but then again
some people they have they feel that
they've been wronged in their in their
lives and there's the sense of justice
that needs to be there
and i can't interact with the world
unless i think that there's karmic
punishment
happening because like i i don't have
the resources to get back to at my
attacker
but karma's going to take care of it so
there are some people who
who uh they're trapped in their own
deception
and they're happy being there and that's
that's a disturbing thing
sometimes i you know when you when you
practice this enough you find that you
need to actually
vent to people who also practice it
because uh it can kind of mess with your
mind when you start realizing
how many confidently
confidently i don't mean the word
ignorant in a bad way
look up the definition that's how i'm
using it confidently
ignorant people navigating the world and
voting and they're teaching their kids
these things
and we're we're in a tough spot
things are not looking good for for
humanity here
we need to get our [ __ ] together so
um people with people who are
approaching
these conversations with others that
they disagree with from a place of love
and empathy
and they use these tools and they can
they can stick in the conversation long
enough to keep their own ego
out of it and be a mirror to the person
that they're speaking to
that is what i think is going to help
break the impasse that we're currently
in
and again this isn't just something for
atheists or the street epistemologists
the street epistemology community is
developing these tools
but we want people across the spectrum
to learn them and not just learn them
use them and maybe even help us develop
them
further that's that's the conundrum that
i think we're at now like
we've been developing this thing and i
think we've got it pretty good and we
may
look back in five years and just cringe
at the way that we're doing it but
that's okay like we're heading in the
right direction
people are learning it and people are
being entertained by it and people are
kind of curious about it
and they're seeing these videos and and
maybe even having good conversations
but if we can't get people from
the understanding phase to the usage
phase
it's not going to really make much of a
difference we need to actually start
using it and implementing it
and teaching people how to do it and
make it acceptable
to have a 30 minute respectful dialogue
on one claim
rather than jumping jumping from one
claim to the other and it
you know it you know going for views and
and the more bombastic this conversation
is the more people will look at it
that's that's crushing us right now
that's crushing that's cr uh
okay i'll stop talking about that that
that's my little hobby horse
cool um i i had a question um
and jen actually like that just when i
was thinking it he dropped the quote
from ken wilbur that
went along the uh the lines of um no one
is uh smart enough to be 100 wrong
right it's kind of like that you know
people the broken clock thing tells the
time right twice type thing
um and so do you think there's a risk at
like if someone has the wrong
epistemology or not a clear one
dismissing their worldview wholesale
even though they might arrive at
the truth through a various different
means like they might have stumbled on
it
and if you just sort of like oh you know
you don't have to write epistemology
go away and then that could be an area
that you're not even focused on because
it's not an interest
so do you think there's a risk to this
method yes so
what i think you're getting at there is
let me summarize what i think you're
saying and then correct me if this isn't
it that's like an essay question too
but um what i think you're saying is
could somebody use the approach of
street epistemology
and lower a person's or help a person
lower their own confidence
in a claim that they think is true and
it really is true
that that can that can absolutely happen
um and it does occasionally happen and
when it does i i feel a little bad
but again i don't really know what the
truth is either but um
somebody could discover that i have an
unreliable way of concluding that god is
real
and because i've determined oh gosh that
really is a horrible
methodology i should probably be less
certain in that claim
the claim could still be factually true
but what we're hoping with this with
this approach is that
we can maybe this is sort of like a
process of elimination of methodologies
okay like well faith as i'm defining it
there is of just believing without
evidence maybe that's like an unreliable
thing
but what's a better way of justifying my
reasons
than faith for that claim maybe i can be
inspired to go find better
reasons and more reliable epistemologies
for confirming those reasons and i can
really have a
a really truly justified confidence in
this claim but that is a risk like
um there's one video that i uploaded
where it was like a 10 minute talk and
there was this woman walking around this
campus
and she was um she was trying to get
people to register to vote
that's that's that's an extremely
valuable thing
and she walked up to me i think it was
our second talk the first talk was about
karma or something
or the law of attraction but she wanted
to talk about why everybody should vote
and by the end of a 10-minute talk she
said
maybe it's really not so important that
people vote or not
and i let her walk away with that
thought because i'm sort of a purist in
that way like
let her let her go and figure it out
now you know maybe we lost out on her
registering five or ten more people
for voting that day um there could be
some serious
or significant um fallout i suppose of
backing off on claims that are true but
because we have an unreliable
epistemology we lower our confidence in
it
i think that can happen but i guess i'm
optimistic
i think that that risk is is
a lot it's a lot less of an issue
than running around with beliefs that
we're certain are true because they're
based on really
faulty epistemologies but i'm one i'm
willing to you know
we we have people who are watching what
we're doing in street epistemology
and they're con some some people are
very excited about it like i am
and some people have some concerns about
it too we don't just shun the people who
have criticisms we want to encourage
that
this approach has gotten better from
people surfacing their concerns about
the approach
pull up a video from five years ago of
somebody doing street epistemology
and then try pulling up a video of it
today and i think you'll notice
that it's moving in the right direction
great question by the way these are
really good questions um
like if anyone has any uh questions so
rain i want to hold on to that question
i
don't have another juicy question the
chat's going crazy right now so i can't
even follow it
um so yeah maybe something about bias
that's what's coming up
uh to piggyback on what you just said um
and so i have an acting background in
improv and whatnot
and then one thing when you go into
improv especially you really get a
sensitivity
like a somatic sensitivity on status and
like status games
and then when when you kind of then you
kind of sniff out when people are
playing status games
um so i want i wonder if there's like a
status bias
in in something like so michael uh
i think bachmann he's a conspiracy
theorist political scientist and he has
a term called stigmatized knowledge
and basically it's knowledge that it
kind of exists outside of like
established institutions like academia
or uh you know like new york times or
whatever
so these are like wild conspiracy
theories woo all that type of stuff
and i noticed that there's like a bias
towards stigmatized knowledge that some
people have it's like a knee-jerk
reaction anything that falls outside
of established authority is just forget
about it
and then there's the on the flip side
there's people that anything that is
from established authority they just
just need your rejection of it
and i find like there's like a status
move on either something weirdly on
either
either side of it so i'm wondering if
street epistemology um flags that kind
of like inherent
bias because i know i don't know about
the the sc community but i know people
on the new atheist community they had
sort of that
anything that stigmatized knowledge i'm
not even going to look at it um
in case a point like uh the q anon i'm
definitely not a q an honor but they
were talking about
epstein for example like almost a year
before he he was
kind of brought into lightweight but he
did um and if you just dismiss
that whole movement you might have
missed something that was happening
there
i'm i'm not entirely sure what you're
asking me so can you phrase it as a
question
yeah so i guess um
how uh like bias and like an under
an attachment to status could make you
dismiss
certain claims yeah and then does street
epistemology
bring awareness to your own bias it
definitely
well from i can only sort of answer that
for myself it's definitely
it's definitely brought attention to my
own bias so like for example i was
actually reluctant to talk about my view
of james and peter because they're
friends of mine
we've hung out together you know we we
help each other occasionally on on
various projects
not so much james but probably more
peter but um
i see i see the the the liability that
bias has
and i'm i guess personally i'm sort of
willing to acknowledge it
and try to overcome it but it's it's
it's alluring
bias is alluring you might think
something is more true because the
person that tweeted it has more
followers
than you would expect or something like
that or they have a blue check mark
so yeah i think there is a tendency to
uh
to to weight the things that we're
hearing more
there's definitely a i think a
psychological tendency to give more
weight to the things that
just confirm what we already think is
the case
but that is that is definitely something
that we're aware of when we're having
these conversations sometimes we have
entire
conversations about bias
i think i uploaded a video where that's
all we talked about it was in the
context of like uh
school exams or something but it became
useful later when we shifted to his
claim that god was real
and we started talking about well look
what bias do i have as a questioner what
bias do you have is the claimant
how do we mitigate our biases how do we
try to account for those
um my friend reed who's actually in here
i know he was doing a virtual reality
essie i think he was testing out using
vr goggles and
you can't really you can go out in
public but some people don't want to
and he had this wonderful conversation
with these young people
he was in a vr room and what was the
claim like
he noticed uh the the this girl that he
was talking with
said that uh she saw a tick tock where
somebody was moving things with their
mind
and though i think one of the main
justifications for thinking that it was
true is because
this person had a lot of followers so
this is something that we see time and
time again in these interactions and
yeah we definitely want to
acknowledge it and point it out but not
in a way where it's demeaning
it's like you know if you were raised in
a different culture do you think that
you might be viewing your claim
differently today
that's a question that we often ask that
kind of gets to the heart of bias
and this goes to your point too that it
would be good that a lot of the mega
tribes had this tool
because they might have a bias that's
opposite than you know the bias that or
someone from the atheist camp uh and
then they can apply it
to each other yeah what i'm hoping is
that there
there will be people there will be
there's probably
there are probably skeptical emotionally
intelligent people
and every tribe on your sheet and tribes
that you haven't even mentioned yet
um i'm i'm hopeful that
this method will appeal to those folks
and they bring it in so like a
almost like a trojan horse of sorts but
like it's not a nefarious trojan horse
because i think
like it's a really respectful useful
tool
um when i hear people critique the
method they almost always
don't fully understand it or maybe
they're thinking about like a an older
description of what this approach is or
maybe they've seen people who hold their
views
get challenged in a way that makes them
uncomfortable because
oh you're just picking on somebody
because they're they're not as they're
not as well versed in this topic or
something
i'm optimistic that people will see the
value of this tool regardless of what
mimetic tribe that you're in and they'll
grasp it and they'll help us develop it
this has always been sort of a community
thing and i don't anticipate that ever
changing
yes we've started a non-profit for this
uh in which
by the way i'm not talking i'm this is
just anthony as as somebody who's an
aficionado of se
talking to you peter um but we do have a
non-profit
for for uh um you know trying to try to
put some money behind this trying to
study this trying to help
get this out to people regardless of
what tribe you're in
i don't care what tribe you're in if you
want to learn this method
and promote it to members of your own
tribe i'm i'm
going to be there to help you do that i
want to help you i don't care i don't
care what tribe you're in
i want people to learn this approach
so we are at the hour um
we're not in any rush here and there's
still a few questions do you want to
stay another 50 minutes or you want to
close it off
however long it takes let's get through
them all i mean i'm cool cool
so well i've been wanting to talk about
this for a while so this this is really
kind of cathartic
for me too cool because it's getting
getting juicy so we'll be here another
15 30 minutes uh
feel free to go as you wish yeah um
albert kim you had something about
values which is kind of cool
um if you want to speak on that
oh oh yeah oh sorry i i completely
forgot what you're
what you're talking about oh yeah so you
had a question on
about neo-nazis using it and which
gesture towards uh
values oh yeah also i was uh picking up
on what reign
uh was asking her question was uh is
street epistemology
moral and there's a bit of an argument
and um well
not an argument like uh you know coming
to a greater truth and
my stance was i believe that uh
it's not inherently moral uh it's not
necessarily coming to
something higher or better because i
believe that a skilled practitioner can
bypass
truth seeking and weaponize sc so they
could
like uh they could give off the pretense
that they're seeking a greater truth
while manipulating someone else so i was
wondering your thoughts on that
yeah that's a really good point and it's
something that we we frequently discuss
in the various sc communities whether
it's reddit or discord or facebook or
whatever um or even privately we have
chats like
how can we make this more ethical how
can we
how can we build in an ethical component
to this
i don't know the answer to that other
than
maybe pointing you to the things that
you may notice that we're trying
in our interactions one thing that at
least i try to do
is i try to be extremely transparent
when i when i start maybe people don't
understand what i do but i
usually like start up a conversation
with somebody i have a camera and i'll
explain that i'm i'm looking to surface
a claim that they make that they think
is true
that i can respectfully challenge with
questions so i try to be very
um i guess like
i try to over ex may sometimes even over
explain but i try to explain what
they're getting into
and and having them consent in now they
may still
be consenting to something that they
think is what's going to happen
like they think that maybe this is a
little puff piece and i can sort of
share my narrative my story
and i'm gonna get this nice warm fuzzy
feeling and then by the end of it
they're like oh gosh like i didn't
realize i was gonna go that way
i suppose that could happen um there
have been times where people said
um i think i'd rather look at your
videos first and then come back and do a
talk
and people have done that and they don't
come back or people have done that and
they do come back
so um
i think trying to explain
exactly what you're attempting to do
with these questions is probably one
that one of the things that
helps make this more ethical but
i also think that if you over explain
what you're doing you can confuse people
and that you don't want to confuse
people i don't i want i don't want
anyone confused
i want clear-headed rationally thinking
as best as possible and try to minimize
the emotion
of the talk as much as possible so um
like tricking somebody into a dialogue
is not something that i'd recommend
obtaining consent i think is really
important and maybe on the on the flip
side of that
after the talk ask them if they want to
ask you
questions back because it can be a
two-way and then
give them a way to contact you later
because sometimes these conversations
can be so
um unnerving maybe
like they're very thought provoking
conversations and if if you
suddenly discover after a 10-minute talk
i can't justify this belief not only to
that stranger with the camera that was
asking me these questions
but i can't justify it to myself anymore
that could be extremely that could be
extremely upsetting to people
who have views that are tied to their
identity
so myself and i think the the community
the community and at large were open to
considering ways to make this
more ethical just one more thing on that
unless you want to go deeper
i think it's kind of interesting that
this topic of the morality of
the approach or the ethics of it comes
up
for street epistemology and it doesn't
come up with
debate or arguing or or ridiculing
people really seem to be concerned about
the ethics of it when they watch the
encounters or they see what we're doing
with this
um which i think might suggest that
there's something really profound about
it um
but then again like we may look back in
a number of years and think
uh you really missed some critical
things you should have said this you
should have done that
maybe maybe um we reach a point where
there's a code of ethics or something
but you have to remember
this these are just people that have
that have read a couple books
and have started having talks and we're
kind of coalescing as a community
this is this is we're at the very early
stages
of this thing and i i don't know where
it's going
i i think i know where it's going in
terms of the culture war and all this
um but it's gonna it's gonna keep
evolving it's evolved tremendously
in the last five years
all right uh jeff falloff albert
um yeah um yeah that was awesome thank
you anthony um so um
just uh the thing that i got from that
is um you know because when i think
about this i think that we're all
very prone to biases so i think it's
like
it's just very difficult for us to
go into any one of the like like a
street epistemology session
and and really in truly good faith
not be trying to convert someone because
you know because like
everyone has their own you know everyone
has their own belief structures and it's
and we could we could say we could
profess that oh i'm trying to get to a
higher truth
i i think that it's extremely difficult
for that to be the case
yeah so i'll just think yeah you know
that's just what i thought about this no
i think that's a really good point
because
uh you know some of us can be
once you do this enough especially if
it's a repetitive claim that people make
like living in texas i run into a lot of
theists
i've been i've i've become really really
good at
having conversations with theists and
driving
fairly quickly down to the to the
reliability of their method
and possibly leaving them with a pebble
in their shoes so that they can figure
it out on their own
that might also sort of lean towards the
ethics of this is like
generally when we have a conversation
with somebody and they discover on their
own
using their own terminology and reasons
and methods and
it's not a misrepresentation at all it's
like we want to try to be a mirror to
the to the stuff that we're hearing from
the person
once they discover or they begin to sort
of realize that maybe
i can't justify my confidence in this
claim that's typically when we
end the talk so that they can go and
think about it or maybe talk to a pastor
or an imam or or sit on it for a year
before they feel comfortable talking
about it again
um i think it would be harder to
to um yeah i think it would be harder to
say that this is an ethical
endeavor if you noticed us
taking advantage of somebody who's in a
a state of doubt
that i think that's crossing a line
there i i hope we never see essie reach
the point where
people are weaponizing it but you have
to remember it is a tool
it can be weaponized but like i said i
think in order to be good at it
you you sort of have to approach it from
a place of empathy and i don't know if
you can
can you still be empathetic and
unethical
maybe you can i think it might be a
little bit more difficult
yeah awesome thank you so much anthony
sure thing oh i was gonna say can i just
add one more thing like
um a good question to ask if you are
wondering about whether it's ethical to
challenge somebody on their views
is you can just explain to them totally
what you're planning to do
i learned this technique it's called
street epistemology some people even are
wondering whether it's ethical
it's where you ask questions and it
might leave you in a state of doubt or
wonder
but then again if you share too much you
could be you could be priming them for
that kind of response so
this this is very tricky um
this is a very good question to ask like
say something like or ask something like
is it important for you that your
beliefs are as close to the factual
truth of the matter as possible
do you value that and
and see what they say you may be
surprised by the response that you get
but generally if somebody says yeah like
i do want to believe
i want my beliefs to align with truth as
much as possible
that's usually a green light if i'm ever
in doubt whether i should engage with
somebody
that's usually something that i'll i'll
try
if they say that they want to believe
true things and they're willing to pay
the
they're willing to rebuild if they have
to and maybe pay the cost
of that then i usually progress but i go
at the speed that they're comfortable
with
that's another i guess challenge of this
i'm sorry to kind of i feel like i'm
rambling here
but i also feel like i'm sharing some
useful stuff um
it can be really tempting to go really
fast at this approach when you get good
at it
because you know it's like the writing's
on the wall it's so evident
but they just haven't discovered it yet
so um sometimes you can be so
proficient with this approach that
you can maybe you can actually hurt
people by doing it
so check with you check with your
conversation partner frequently
do you mind i if i ask you two more
questions or
you know i noticed that you kind of
crossed your arms there would you like
to wrap it up or
is this getting too uncomfortable for
you you can do that so check in with
your conversation partner and make sure
that they're okay
with what you're doing i'm wondering if
there's a um
another value that's needed that's
equally as strong as the value for
truth seeking truth uh because what you
described there kind of relates to what
paul asked about emotional intelligence
kind of like
having a feel of where someone's at um
and having care
learning to read people a little bit too
um
yeah so the question is you're just
instrumentalizing that skill set in
order to get to the truth
um that's one thing or do you think
there has to be an equal value
that engenders that care naturally
for the practitioner you mean yes
i don't think i don't i don't see how
you could become a practitioner of this
method if you don't yourself value the
truth of the matter
so i think that's probably a
prerequisite is that you yourself value
truth
and you yourself are willing to pay the
cost of abandoning a view
that you can't justify to yourself even
though it might ostracize you from
the very tribe that you identify with um
how many of us who are watching are
listening had had to do that it's not an
easy thing
you have to rebuild you might have to
find new friends you might have to learn
learn a new a new language so to speak
like new new lingo
um it could be scary to to realize that
i can't justify this belief and i need
to find a new tribe
a tribe of people who question who value
who value uncertainty and doubt and and
see dogma is problematic
they're the community is there we're out
here there are people who do that
but that that's sort of as a
prerequisite you have to value truth and
i think you have to
you have to respect that other people's
value of truth are different
and and uh
and respect that as much as you can it
could be upsetting when you see people
who are like
i don't care if it's true or not i can
sleep better at night when i go to bed
thinking that
the creator of the universe is watching
over me and they really mean it
it could be it could be a little
disheartening but
i guess i'm more optimistic that more
people do
want to believe the truth of the matter
despite the cost i guess let me see if i
can rephrase
my question is that like truth is
a key value of a street epistemologist
the key value of yourself
and it's a value that um that you're you
know gesturing towards strongly when you
are
engaged in this method but does it need
to be
held by another value um
you know like something that a value
that naturally engenders
care empathy you know like paul evander
clay talked about love
um or are you just instrumentalizing
empathy and all this stuff in order to
get
that value of truth leveraging empathy
in order to have a really good talk
i mean that's probably something every
every person who learns this approach is
going to have to answer for themselves
like
am i leveraging the empathy that i have
that i'm capable of
to challenge people's views that i
happen to disagree with i think it can
be used that way
you can weaponize this approach you can
you can probably use it for nefarious
means um
i mean i i don't think that i'm doing
that like i i think that when i'm
talking with people about their views
i'm genuinely interested in their
reasons and their methods
and helping them discover that their bad
reasons like unr
uh their um their poor reasons
and their unreliable epistemologies like
that that excites me
when i can see somebody thinking about a
deeply held belief
and giving it some thought like hmm
you're asking some good questions here
like that's a really fun i mean it feels
good
but um you know on the same hand
you have to sort of recognize that your
questions
the the types of questions that we ask
can be problematic for some people
you could actually harm people
i think with this approach you have to
be focused you have to be
really paying attention to the dialogue
that you're having
i think that that's that's my own view i
think that there are some practitioners
of us here like
forget the consent forget the ethics of
it like i just want to
see people squirm a little bit when i
ask them you know
why they're not wearing their mask at
walmart or something you know
there are some people who sort of
enjoyed that but uh
i don't know like par a big part of me
sort of realizes that uh
i i am very likely
holding views of reality that i cannot
justify to myself
um i i want people to help me figure
that out so i can stop
putting as much weight on those views
that are influencing my behavior
and i guess i sort of assume that people
feel the same way but
you can't you really need to sort of
have a
almost maybe sort of like an agreement
at the start this is what i'd like to
talk about here's the potential outcomes
maybe
i'll be here for you after if you need
it
um but whether or not yeah maybe
you're asking some good questions i i
don't know if i could answer that
question any further than i've already
brought you there
and i guess the metaphor that comes to
mind is like martial artists at least a
traditional
martial artist like they teach you to be
effective with your body
um but they have you know this whole
ecology of values that are
surrounded by that like honor integrity
um in order not to disabuse your
or abuse i should say that skill set
well street epistemology people who are
into psychotherapy may notice some
similarities
i'm actually curious if there's anyone
here who who has experience in
motivational interviewing or
or psychotherapy
there seems to be some parallels there
but one thing that i noticed that
people who are psychotherapists they
have a formal education
there there may actually be a code of
ethics
i don't actually know if that's the case
but i would think that if you're a
professional
psychotherapist you you probably
is that the case i don't know like i'm
thinking that um there's a professional
aspect to some of these
techniques where um there's some
oversight there's some there's some
standards
and we don't have that here like again
people are reading books they're
watching videos and they're attempting
it and we're like seeing what's working
and what's not and we're refining it
um there's no ethics board at the moment
for se
i don't know if there ever will be or if
there should be maybe there maybe
maybe we'll be kicking ourselves that we
didn't set something up sooner i don't
know
but i think if we always at the back of
my mind i'm thinking
if we if we tighten this down too much
at the start
it could limit our ability to creatively
evolve it
so maybe at the start it might be a
little bit unethical i don't know
like maybe the ethicalness of this will
sort of increase as our
as our formalization of the process
increases too i'm not exactly sure but
um
the the thing that's getting people's
attention and the thing that's
developing this approach further
is that there really are no rules at the
moment
i i don't know if that's a good or a bad
thing i'm my sense is that it's a really
good thing
because
oop uh i think we lost you anthony
can anyone else here anthony give me a
little no
um wait
a couple of moments and then we might
close out because we
passed some 50 minute mark
i was getting some juicy territory
storm took him out maybe thunder strike
hope it wasn't a direct one
okay so um i'm going to put anthony in
the the waiting room bring him back
in see if he
comes back if not
anthony are you there
yeah mute yourself
oh you're on mute still anthony
you gotta unmute okay there we go there
we go you're back
you think i'm a novice of this um i just
got up to check and see what was going
on and it turns out that uh my wife just
got home from work and she said that
it's raining outside so it's
i guess it might be weather related um i
don't know where i dropped off there but
yeah um
yeah like um i can't i can't remember we
dropped off either
uh how about uh we end off with one more
question
and then um oh yeah the thing i wanted
to say
with that is that just to summarize uh
what i heard
sort of like a code of ethics hasn't
been developed or hasn't
naturally emerged that's kind of
commonly agreed upon because the focus
has been refining the method and the
excitement about that
and then there's an interesting point
that you made that if you focus too much
on the code of ethics that kind of might
um ameliorate uh the focus on actual
the actual kind of improvement of the
method that's my concern
uh i don't know if it's warranted or not
like maybe we can do both at the same
time where
we're integrating a code of ethics into
the application of the approach
while at the same time we're still
encouraging experimentation and
development
i mean maybe it's possible my sense is
that
this is maybe where it dropped off but i
think my sense is that
we're probably in a really good spot now
where
all sorts of people from around the
world and all sorts of different tribes
are learning the approach and they're
practicing it
and then hopefully they're sharing what
seems to be working what's not
like that's that's a really good spot to
be in but will we always be here
i don't know we might actually see some
sort of
codified standard of ethics or something
to be a practitioner but
like okay so we come up with it how do
you enforce it like are we going to
throw people in jail for
you know not not following the street
epistemology code of ethics
so it it almost seems kind of funny
but i understand people's concerns about
it i absolutely do
[Music]
so we'll try to uh end uh in about eight
minutes we'll get one more question in
um sure kevin deland i really i don't
want to hear your question you got a few
juicy ones um
uh i know i'm saying juicy a lot for
whatever reason but uh okay thank you
um sure how's it going everyone
hi thanks anthony i've watched your a
bunch of your videos a few years ago
so oh gosh um maybe watch something more
recent hopefully
i like to think it's changed a little
bit soon
okay um anthony are you doxtastically
open to the belief
that there is no such thing as objective
truth
or that trying to find something like
objective truth
is not like useful
i'm i'm open to both
i'm open to both ideas that uh
that maybe subjective truth is the best
way to navigate the world
for human beings that uh hey you know as
long as you get value from it
and and you know
you're less stressed you know as you're
navigating the world like
i guess it all depends on what your
values are like if i value
longevity and uh
i got yeah i don't want to get too far
off our field but yeah
i think i'm open to the idea that
subjective truth
might be more valuable than objective
truth
there was there was a second piece uh to
your question there what was the other
one
yeah so um or
sorry it's kind of dark here um the
so the example you used earlier was like
the
box of tic-tacs and knowing whether or
not there is an even or odd number
um and i think it
in my opinion it's kind of a big stretch
to say like um oh
that knowing the how many
tic tacs are in a box can be
extrapolated to things sort of like oh
what
should be done or what kind of
prescriptive things
like we should have a value in objective
truth um and
one example i sort of thought of was do
you know the
it might be insist uh thinking fast and
slow but
the people if you try and get people to
like identify
like describe or draw the back of a
penny with abe lincoln's face and like
where the different things are
right they don't really pick up on those
little details
right so to me it seems like like the
tic tac box might be something
um like you know trivial that is not
really useful to
for people to know um
do you sorry i don't i don't know if
that was a question but do you have any
thoughts
i do i mean the the tic tac test
of asking people if they think the total
number of pieces is either
even or odd and it can't simultaneously
both be both
is a very simple example
to try to see if a person agrees that
truth is objective
maybe it's not the best example i mean
i've used examples in the field where i
said something like uh
like i met this one woman on the trail
and she
was here from poland or something and
she specifically wanted to see
armadillos
and then we started talking and she
started going relativistic
she later asked me not to upload the
video so i'm just i'm
it tears me apart but we started talking
about armadillos and if she thinks that
they're live bearers or egg layers
and she's like i don't know what i'm not
sure i'm like i actually don't know what
it is either
however would you agree that it's one or
the other and it can't be both
so you can still use real world examples
like for example
um did russia
did trump collude with russia either he
did or he didn't
like i mean there's a there's a factual
matter to it
but um it's hard to
explore the quality of a person's
reasons for thinking
that something is true if they if they
defer to the subjectivity
of our reality so for example
a very good question we might ask
somebody is like you know the hindu is
just as confident that their god is real
and they also base their
they also use faith to come to their
conclusion and
for somebody who would answer the
question about the tic tacs and say
it could both be even and odd
simultaneously
when you ask them a question that we
call the outsider test for faith they
will often say well
the hindu is correct and i'm correct
we're both correct that our gods are
real
even though these are contradictory gods
and and i think the
at least the christian might say well
there's only one god
where's the hindu might the hindu might
allow for the the christian god
so one thing that we're trying to do
with with se
and sometimes it's a liability maybe but
we're trying to take really complex
topics
and and make them understandable
so that we can discuss the beliefs that
we're holding and the confidence that
we're putting in the beliefs
um is it is the best is it the best tool
or the best example the most realistic
thing
no but it's very simple and it usually
helps getting people thinking about
these these views
of objective and subjective truth
um yeah thank you for your
response um i should probably say um
probably after this
you know i don't want to take any peter
do people go
can people go somewhere after this talk
to keep talking about this do you have a
place for them or
yeah we have a discord that has video
channels um that you can beautiful
yeah so the link on if i'm not over
there
because we'll be eating dinner soon but
um there will more than likely be people
from the sc community that will head
over there to answer questions like that
oh the store is going to get invaded by
the uh
you want that yeah i do yeah that's what
we want that's what we want
yeah yeah um
yeah so i'm going to close out in a
moment is there any uh
kind of thoughts you want to leave us
with for the people who are listening on
the recording and people in the
room right now um
any thoughts um
i don't know i mean we're looking for
outside perspectives to help make this
better i think that's been a continuing
theme throughout this whole interview
like
you know this this was largely started
in the atheist community but it
we don't want it to stay there like i
think that could be that could be the
worst thing for street epistemology
to to stay in one cloistered into one
tribe
like we want people from around the if
you're in black lives matter
join the street epistemology server if
you're if you're a trump fan
join the street epistemology server um
that would be my advice
is help us make this better and and
bring these tools to your tribes
so that you can challenge them on the
claims that they're making
and uh two things that i'll kind of like
suggest is a potential uh collaboration
with the stone
and the sc um one one thing um
uh edward rush uh the guy who created uh
empathy circles that dan was talking
about uh he's gonna come to the store
and he's gonna do training empathy
circle training for the stoa
and that's like a technique um it's like
gamifies carl rogers
active listening where you just repeat
what the other person said in your own
words so they feel understood
um just to kind of build that listening
understanding muscle so we're going to
get training in that here
and i'm a fan of the um sc technique and
that would be cool if there could be
some kind of sc training for the stoa
village um i'd be very because as you
can kind of tell just from the questions
that you're getting we got like a lot of
juicy oddball people uh like coming in
this place it's very delicious
yeah they come from we like just because
the the
the audience and the guests i have here
they're from all kind of the medic
tribal constellation so we get like pick
all sorts of interesting people um so
yeah i would love to have some kind of
training even if it's informal yeah um
we have people from the community i
noticed dolly's in here he's been having
is it weekly dolly maybe just nod your
head because i'm watching you
weekly training he's nodding his head
weekly training sessions
where people interested in this approach
can
can practice street epistemology
there are there's an effort to develop a
course
so that we can like a web app type of
course for people to learn this approach
and then uh by all means please watch
the videos like watching people talk
about all different types of claims
and having them explored where it's not
getting heated it's not getting
contentious
um the rabbit hole goes very deep for
street epistemologies let me put it that
way
there are people who are very eager
to teach you how to do this and uh
and help us make it better yeah and then
the
other uh um thing i i and this is
something we can talk offline
is having maybe some kind of like battle
royale where people like christians paul
vander clay comes in and some
sd comes in and they have displayed the
method have conversations
before i'm so glad that you mentioned
that because i've been talking to some
of the people who
have been involved in this community for
a number of years
and uh i don't want to take credit for
it but i don't remember exactly who said
it but somebody has suggested
and i love this idea like maybe the
street epistemology community can be the
place where people from these different
memetic tribes
come to in order to bounce their ideas
off of people
and you don't even necessarily have to
know the approach
we might actually be able to assign a
facilitator of some sorts where
there can be an intermediary talking to
the black lives matter
uh proponent and somebody from antifa
maybe or something like that
i don't know um it's conceivable with
the technology that we have and
and the ease with which we can
communicate where maybe we can bring
these different groups together
in the in these different sc communities
and sort of hash these things out
and maybe record it wouldn't that be
cool to to
to show people from these different
tribes talking respectfully and making
progress
yeah totally um and if you ever want to
use a still as a prototype or you know
test something out
uh it's yours uh to do so so
i'll make some uh closing announcements
but anthony thanks so much for
coming out today my friend that was fun
thank you peter for having me out it was
a blast
honestly and i feel like i got a lot off
my chest
and again i haven't really thought it
through all the way but um this has been
really helpful in my own personal
development so thank you for having me
yeah my pleasure and that's what we love
here putting all of us at the edge of
our thinking
um so uh you can check out the discord
right there
uh you you go to the rules you have to
give it a thumbs up then you get access
to all the channels including the video
channels
uh if you like what we're doing here at
the stoa you can visit us on patreon and
give us some support uh upcoming events
we got one in 30 minutes
how to be a meta modern thought leader
uh wtf with jason
fox that's at eight pm eastern time
tomorrow uh deep politics with peter
dale scott he's a political scientist
uh and he talks about political
practices and arrangements that
are deliberate or not that are usually
repressed in public discourse rather
than acknowledged
so this is deep politics the deep state
kind of gets to conspiratorial
territories but from first principle
thinking
really excited about that and you can
rcp here street epistemologies
all are welcome to these events so you
can kind of challenge our speakers
that being said thank you again anthony
thank you everyone for coming out today
thank you bye y'all